We move now on to the last part of this lecture
about file sharing and protection. So how
do we share and protect files among different
users?
The idea is that the file system should facilitate
should provide mechanisms so that who create
who owns a specific file is able to decide
what should be done with the file and who
has the right to operate on that file.
So this kind of functionality is actually
given by the file system.
And the first thing that we have to mention
here is that each file can be accessed in
different ways the file system might let
you read a file, but not modify it. It might
actually allow you to modify the file or to
execute the file if it's a binary if it's
a program that can be executed or a script might
allow you to append to the file or delete
or list all the files in a folder. So how
you access files depends on how the operating
system allows you
to access each specific type of file
or directory. So the common way to go
is to have three let's say big high level modes
of access read, write and execute, and three
different classes of users. This is what you
have in Unix systems. That is what we are
using mostly here for our examples, so you
can define this read, write and execute
privileges for three different groups.
One, the first one is the owner and it
means that it applies to
(the read, write and execute permissions) apply
to the owner of the file. Then there is the
group. So each file is associated to
can be associated to a group and the group
is a set of users.
And in that case you can specify this read
write and execute privileges for the group.
And the last one is the public
For all the three of them, it's always the
same. It's whether they can read, write, or
execute
the specific file.
Which one applies to you depends on who you
are. If you are the owner of the file, then
what applies to you is the owner access.
If you belong to the group, you are not the
owner, but you belong to the group that is
registered for the file
that is the set of privileges that applies
to you. If none of the first two, then it's
a public one
Here you have a small example saying that
the owner can read, write and execute.
The users that belong to the group can read
write but not execute and the users that
are not the owner and do not belong to
the group
then they cannot read and write, but they
can execute. It is just an example.
One clarification here:
In practice, in Unix systems, what you can
do with the files usually depends on the permissions
you set on the directory that contains the
files. OK, but I don't expect now you
to be too specific about these things. If I ask
something. If there are exercises about permissions
and I show you the
different privileges for a file. If you are
assuming something on the folder that contains
the file and so on, then say it. But otherwise,
let's just assume that for each file, what
is applied is
the set of permissions you see for the file,
which again in Unix system might not always
be the case because there are rules about
permissions set on the folder and what applies
to all the files in the
in such folder
Here you have an example of the same thing
but under Windows so just to show you that
this is not just something that happens in
Unix systems.
And this is
the content of a folder. So here you see that
now you have this
there are 10 entries here let's for a moment,
ignore the first one so you are left with
nine and here the first three are the owner,
then the second group of three is the group
and the last group of three is the public,
and when they are set it means that that privilege
is granted, and when they're not it means
that it is not. So. For example, if you take
this file
it's basically saying that the owner can do
everything read write and execute while both group
and public can only read and execute, but
they cannot modify the file.
The first bit here, it specifies whether
it's a file or a directory. If it's not
set, it's a file. If you see a d, that
is a directory. So open your Unix system,
that in principle we are using to test a bit
what we discuss in the course, and list
the files that we have in a folder and you
will see that you can see all these permissions
for each
individual file